Fairfield Collection
Fairfield Collection
1804-1950
10 linear ft.
Records of Fairfield Academy and Fairfield Medical College, Herkimer County, New York, and the personal papers of Dr. William Mather, Alonzo C. Mather, Albert B. Watkins, and other families and individuals connected with the school and town.
148968
Biographical History
Fairfield Academy, located in the town of Fairfield in Herkimer County, New York, was incorporated in 1803. The Academy had several instructors in medical subjects, including anatomy, pharmacy, medicine, surgery, and obstetrics. In 1812, 43 students were studying medical subjects and the Academy applied for a charter as a medical college in order to be able to grant M.D. degrees to its students. The charter was granted under the name of "The College of Physicians and Surgeons of the Western District of New York," but the institution was commonly known as Fairfield Medical College. It was the second medical college to be chartered in the state and the 11th in the United States. The faculty was composed of eminent physicians and physician-instructors, and the college acquired an excellent reputation. By 1833 the school had over 200 students and over its life granted more than 600 M.D. degrees, 18 of whom went on to become professors in other medical colleges. (Of the five members of the faculty of the Geneva (N.Y.) Medical College who transferred to the Syracuse University Medical College upon its establishment in 1871, at least three had received their medical training at Fairfield.) Fairfield Medical College closed in 1840, due to competition from other medical colleges opened in New York and surrounding states. In 1812, the trustees of Fairfield Academy, acting on the suggestion of the Rev. Amos G. Baldwin, petitioned Trinity Episcopal Church in Fairfield for a grant of funds to establish a college of liberal culture under Episcopal auspices. This petition was not granted, but in the following year, acting upon another petition suggested by the Rev. Baldwin, the corporation of Trinity church founded a theological school in connection with Fairfield Academy.
The academy was reorganized as the co-educational Fairfield Seminary in 1839, incorporating a "Classical Academy and Female Collegiate Institute," with a teacher training and college preparation curriculum. Its enrollment in 1861 was 551. As new major transportation routes developed in the 19th century, bypassing the town of Fairfield, the academy lost its prominence. It operated as a military academy beginning in 1891 and closed permanently in 1901, largely due to competition from the growing number of high schools in the area.
Dr. William Mather (1802-1890), a descendent of Cotton Mather, was a son of Captain Moses Mather, an early settler of Herkimer County and one of the founders of Fairfield Academy. In 1826, Mather graduated from Fairfield Medical College with the degree of M.D. As he had from boyhood been "an ardent lover of the science of chemistry," he turned his attention to that subject and from 1828 to 1868 was one of the most popular lecturers in this country. He married Mary Ann Buell in 1836, and the two had three children. In 1838 he was appointed instructor in chemistry at the Hamilton (New York) Literary and Theological Seminary and in 1841 was elected professor of chemistry at the Castleton (Vermont) Medical College. From 1852 to 1868 he was professor of chemistry, mineralogy, and geology at Madison (now Colgate) University in Hamilton. He was also the president of Fairfield Seminary for more than a quarter of a century.
Alonzo Clark Mather (1848-1941), an inventor and industrialist, was educated at Fairfield Academy and upon graduation went to work as a clerk in Utica, New York. In 1867 he opened his own mercantile business in Little Falls, New York, and moved to Quincy, Illinois the subsequent year. In 1875 he moved to Chicago and ran a wholesale business under the name Alonzo C. Mather and Company, which imported and manufactured a ladies’ self-lacing glove of his own patent. In 1880, following an incident observing the poor conditions of cattle in railway transport, Mather began work on a more humane stock car, and in the following year started the Mather Humane Stock Transportation Company of Chicago (commonly known as the Mather Stock Car Company) in order to produce these cars. The American Humane Association awarded Mather a medal for the humane treatment of animals in 1883. For many years, Mather endeavored to build a bridge across the Niagara River from Buffalo to Fort Erie, Ontario, which would harness the water currents for electric power; however, a bill from the United States Congress prevented the realization of this idea. He did build Mather Tower in Chicago, which served as the headquarters for the Mather Stock Car Company and is now a Chicago Historic Landmark.
Albert Barnes Watkins (1838-1892), a native of Naples, New York, was a student of Fairfield Seminary who also began teaching at the school. In 1861 he entered Amherst College as a junior and graduated in two years with honors. He returned to Fairfield as a teacher, and in 1863 he married Martha Ann Mather, the daughter of Dr. William Mather. He was the principal of the Hungerford Collegiate Institute in Adams, New York, for twelve years (1870-1882), where he was elected and served two terms as School Commissioner of Jefferson County, and also received the degree of Doctor of Philosophy. In 1882 he became the State Inspector of Teachers' Classes, and from 1884 until his death he served as the Assistant Secretary of the University of the State.
A genealogy of the Buell, Clark, Dresser, Griswold, Mather and Watkins families is available here (if online) or at the end of this finding aid (if in hard copy).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Fairfield Academy series encompasses items relating to the combined history of Fairfield Academy (incorporated 1803), The College of Physicians and Surgeons of the Western District of New York (chartered 1812), and Fairfield Seminary (founded 1813). Included are the correspondence and meeting minutes of the Board of Trustees; materials related to the College of Physicians and Surgeons; items from Fairfield Seminary including a diploma for Burrit D. Case and report cards for Martha Ann Mather; financial material, and published material.
The Fairfield, New York series consists of iems connected to the town of Fairfield, including biographical and genealogical notes from researchers, primarily regarding the Buell and Mather families; legal documents; and materials regarding Trinity Church and the Woman’s Central Association of Relief.
Fairfield Families includes the personal papers of the Buell, Mather, and Watkins families who are connected through the marriages of Dr. William Mather to Mary Ann Buell, whose father Roswell Buell donated land for Fairfield Academy; and of Mather’s daughter Martha Ann to Albert Barnes Watkins. Many of the writers of the letters are already represented in the Library's special collections, especially the Gerrit Smith Collection. No special restrictions.
The Dr. William Mather Papers material contains the personal papers of Dr. William Mather, including his own biographical and genealogical work; family, general and professional correspondence; financial records and writings. There are also many of Dr. Mather's lecture notes in manuscript, including "minutes" of the medical lectures delivered by various doctors at the Fairfield school between 1827 and 1838; account books and journals of the "popular lectures" which he delivered throughout New York State; manuscript notes and letter-press accounts of the history of the Fairfield schools and of the Town of Fairfield, etc. These papers are significant for the revelations they make concerning the early days of the teaching of natural sciences in New York State and the teaching of chemistry in the United States during the first half of the nineteenth century.
The Alonzo C. Mather Papers contain the personal papers of Alonzo Clark Mather, including biographical and genealogical work; family correspondence; general correspondence and subject files; financial material and memorabilia. There is also assorted material related to his various inventions, primarily the humane stock car and the proposed bridge, as well as his professional interests.
The Albert B. Watkins Papers include the correspondence and documents of Albert Barnes Watkins, a notable Fairfield Seminary student and teacher. Among the professional correspondence and the documents are materials relating to Watkins’ capacity as a teacher at Fairfield, as principal of the Hungerford Collegiate Institute in Adams, NY, and as Assistant Secretary of the University of the State.
The Miscellaneous series contains unidentified correspondence and fragments, unsigned manuscripts, assorted printed material, and "Transcripts from Colonial Record” which relates to Edward Griswold (1607-1691), of whom Sarah Buell (née Griswold) (1769-1856) is a descendent.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is divided into the series given above, in ascending chronological order.
Related Material
See also the
Smallwood Collection
, which concerns Amos Eaton and the teaching of the natural sciences in America previous to 1875; Tip of the Hill, by Thomas C. O'Donnell, an informal history of Fairfield Academy and Fairfield Medical College; and "The Pawnee missionaries," a narrative about Martha Ann Mather Satterlee in The Christian keepsake and missionary annual, edited by John Alonzo Clark.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Science and medicine; Buell, Alexander Hamilton.; Clark, John A. (John Alexander); Clark, John A. (John Alonzo), 1801-1843.; Mather, Alonzo C.; Mather, Horace E., 1827-1909.; Mather, Mary Ann Buell.; Mather, Moses, 1774-1832.; Mather, William.; Satterlee, Martha Ann Mather.; Spalding, Lyman, 1775-1821.; Watkins, Albert Barnes.; Watkins, Martha Ann Mather.; Buell family.; Mather family.; Watkins family.; College of Physicians and Surgeons of the Western District of the State of New-York.; Fairfield seminary and military academy, Fairfield, N.Y.; Fairfield Medical College.; Woman's Central Association of Relief.; Cooper, James Fenimore, 1789-1851 -- Criticism and interpretation.; Genealogical correspondence.; Education -- New York (State) -- Herkimer County.; Medical education -- History.; Railroads -- Livestock transportation.; Water-power -- New York (State); Adams (N.Y.); Buffalo (N.Y.); Chicago (Ill.); Fairfield (N.Y.: Town); Fort Erie (Ont.); Herkimer County (N.Y.); Niagara Falls (N.Y. and Ont.); Address books.; Agreements.; Autobiographies (literary works); Blueprints (reprographic copies); Broadsides (notices); Business letters.; Circulars (fliers); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Diaries.; Diplomas.; Genealogies (histories); Greeting cards.; Indentures.; Instructional materials.; Logs (records); Minutes (administrative records); Notebooks.; Obituaries.; Patents.; Photographs.; Report cards.; Scrapbooks.; Sketches.; Summonses.; Telegrams.; Educators.; Industrialists.; Inventors & inventions.; Lawyers.; Physicians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mary Anne Loomis Shepard of Palmdale, California, great-granddaughter of George S. Loomis, pioneer resident of the Town of DeWitt, Onondaga County, New York, 1970.
Diploma gift of Sarah Christensen, 2011..
Inventory
- Fairfield Academy
  - Board of Trustees
    - Correspondence, 1844; 1876; 3 items (Box 1)
    - Meeting minutes, 1811; 1842,; 1845,; undated; 10 items (Box 1)
  - College of Physicians and Surgeons
    - Dr. Spalding's Inaugural Address, 1814; An address delivered at Fairfield VII December MDCCCXIII at the inauguration of the officers of the College of Physicians and Surgeons of the Western District of the State of New-York by Lyman Spalding. Contains original and photocopy; an electronic copy is available via.; 2 items (Box 1)
    - Kappa Alpha Phi Society, 1826; 1830; 4 items (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1827; 1830,; 1880; 3 items (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Reunion and Memorial, 1922-1923; 26 items (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1864; 4 items (Box 1)
  - Fairfield Seminary
    - Catalogs, 1866-1874; 3 items (Box 1)
    - Debate societies, 1862-1865; undated; 8 items (Box 1)
    - Diploma, June 22, 1899; for Burritt D. Case; 1 item (Box 18)
    - Records, 1857-1890; undated; 11 items (Box 1)
    - Report cards, 1853-1859; undated; for Martha Ann Mather, daughter of Dr. William Mather; 8 items (Box 1)
  - Financial material, 1853-1869; 5 items (Box 1)
  - Published material, 1881-1896; 1913,; 1950,; undated; 9 items (Box 1)
- Fairfield, New York
  - Biography and genealogy material, 17 items (Box 1)
    See also Dr. William Mather Papers: Biographical and genealogical material (Box 7) and Alonzo C. Mather Papers: Biographical and genealogical material (Box 8)
  - Correspondence
    - Sale of Martha Watkins' house, 1919-1920; 8 items (Box 1)
    - Town correspondence, 1879; 1884; 2 items (Box 1)
  - Legal material, 1831; 1853,; 1875,; 1877; 4 items (Box 1)
  - Trinity Church, 1837; 1860-1880,; undated; 17 items (Box 1)
  - Woman's Central Association of Relief, 1864-1865; undated; 10 items (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous and fragmentary, 9 items (Box 1)
- Fairfield Families
  - Buell
    - Buell, Alexander Clark (1845-1880) (son of Alexander H. and Harriet Buell), 1852-1876; undated; 11 items (Box 2)
    - Buell, Alexander H. (Hamilton) (1801-1853) (brother of Mary Ann Mather)
      - Correspondence, 1827-1851; 6 items (Box 2)
      - Death of, 1853; includes telegrams and summons; 5 items (Box 2)
    - Buell, Harriet E. (née Gruman) (1819-?) (wife of Alexander H. Buell), 1861-1884; undated; 11 items (Box 2)
    - Buell, Mary Ann (1805-1874), See Mather, Mary Ann (née Buell)
    - Buell, Sarah (née Griswold) (1769-1856) (mother of Daniel, Sarah, Alexander H., and Mary Buell), 1812-1848; 8 items (Box 2)
    - Buell, Sarah (1798-?), See Clark, Sarah (née Buell)
    - Clark, John A. (Alexander) (1833-?) (son of Reverend John Alonzo and Sarah Clark), 1852-1874; undated; 12 items (Box 2)
    - Clark, Reverend John Alonzo (1801-1943) (husband of Sarah Clark), 1831-1834; undated; 7 items (Box 2)
    - Clark, Sarah (née Buell) (1798-?) (sister of Mary Buell)
      - Incoming correspondence, 1838-1851; undated; 8 items (Box 2)
      - Outgoing correspondence, 1839-1855; undated; 13 items (Box 2)
  - Mather
    - Mather, A. B. (Albert Barnes) (1845-?) (son of Jairus and Eliza Mather), 1865-1866; 6 items (Box 2)
    - Mather, Irene (née Argyle Irene Gasper) (1879-1950) (third wife of Alonzo C. Mather), 1914; 13 items (Box 2)
    - Mather, Jairus (1819-1893) (brother of Dr. William Mather), 1853-1862; 4 items (Box 2)
    - Mather, John Alonzo Clark ("Lon") (1848-1941) (son of Dr. William and Mary Mather), See Alonzo C. Mather Papers (Boxes 8-15)
    - Mather, Louise (née Maria Louise Eames) (1840-1920) (second wife of Alonzo C. Mather), 1880-1884; undated; 22 items (Box 2)
    - Mather, Martha Ann (1813-1836) (sister of Dr. William Mather), See Satterlee, Mrs. Benedict (née Martha Ann Mather) (Box 3)
    - Mather, Martha Ann ("Mattie") (1840-1927) (daughter of Dr. William and Mary Mather), See Watkins, Martha Ann ("Mattie") (née Mather) (Boxes 4-6)
    - Mather, Mary Ann (née Buell) (1805-1874) (wife of Dr. William Mather)
      - Incoming correspondence, 1823-1846; 9 items (Box 2)
      - Outgoing correspondence, 1831-1870; undated; 10 items (Box 2)
    - Mather, Martha O. (née Johnson) (?-1879) (first wife of Alonzo C. Mather), 1 items (Box 2)
    - Mather, Moses (1774-1832) (father of Dr. William, Jacob Dresser, Martha Ann, and Jairus Mather), 1804; 1814; 2 items (Box 2)
    - Mather, Sarah (née Dresser) (1779-1843) (mother of Dr. William, Jacob Dresser, Martha Ann, and Jairus Mather), 1853-1858; 10 items (Box 2)
    - Mather, Dr. William (1802-1890), See Dr. William Mather Papers (Boxes 7-8)
    - Mather, Dr. William and Mary (collectively), 1856-1874; 6 items (Box 3)
    - Mather, William Alexander (1837-1908) (son of Dr. William and Mary Mather), 1853-1884; undated; 8 items (Box 3)
    - Satterlee, Mrs. Benedict (née Martha Ann Mather) (1813-1836) (sister of Dr. William Mather), 1828-1835; Died en route to Oregon with the Marcus Whitman expedition in 1836; 12 items (Box 3)
    - W[ickham?], Abbie (niece of Sarah Mather), 1834-1867; undated; 13 items (Box 3)
  - Watkins
    - General biographical facts, 3 items (Box 3)
    - Watkins, Albert Barnes, See Albert B. Watkins Papers (Boxes 16-17)
    - Watkins, Albert Barnes and Martha Ann, 1864-1869; 6 items (Box 3)
    - Watkins, Arthur (circa 1849-1899), 1863-1869; brother of Albert B. Watkins; 23 items (Box 3)
    - Watkins, Mrs. E. H. (née Eveline Hamlin, 1816-1900), 1862-1876; undated; mother of Albert Barnes, Frank H., and Arthur Watkins; 137 items in 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Watkins, Eva (Evelina/Evelyn Mary) (1866-1932), daughter of Albert B. and Martha A. Watkins
      - Correspondence, 1878-1882; 8 items (Box 4)
      - Personal documents, 1882-1884; undated; 5 items (Box 4)
    - Watkins, Frank Alonzo (1875-?), 1880-1923; son of Albert B. and Martha A. Watkins; 15 items (Box 4)
    - Watkins, Frank H. (circa 1846-?), 1862-1868; brother of Albert B. Watkins; 36 items (Box 4)
    - Watkins, Jesse Mather (1868-?), 1879-1923; son of Albert B. and Martha A. Watkins; 7 items (Box 4)
    - Watkins, Martha "Mattie" Ann (1840-1927), daughter of Dr. William and Mary Mather; wife of Albert B. Watkins
      - Correspondence, family
        - Incoming, 1853-1867; 30 items (Box 4)
        - Mather, Alonzo C. (brother), 1864-1914; 4 items (Box 4)
        - Mather, Mary Ann (mother), 1855-1871; 10 items (Box 4)
        - Mather, Dr. William (father), 1857-1880; 72 items in 3 folders (Box 4)
        - Mather, Dr. William (father), 1881-1886; undated; 76 items in 3 folders (Box 5)
        - Parents (collectively), 1864-1874; undated; 24 items (Box 5)
        - Watkins, Albert Barnes (husband), 1859-1862; 25 items in 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Watkins, Albert Barnes (husband), 1863-1865; undated; 12 items (Box 6)
        - Other family, 1852; 1856,; undated; 4 items (Box 6)
      - Correspondence, general
        - A-W, 49 items (Box 6)
        - Dunn, John King, 1853-1855; 10 items (Box 6)
        - Hockley, Thomas and Annie, undated; 7 items (Box 6)
        - Liddell, Mattie (Mrs. J. B. Hull), 1858-1865; 21 items (Box 6)
        - Perkins, Katie, 1856-1867; 33 items (Box 6)
        - Quinby, Libbie, 1862-1869; undated; 13 items (Box 6)
        - Ward, Eliza ("Lizzie"), 1853-1864; 25 items (Box 6)
        - Unidentified, 13 items (Box 6)
      - Printed material, 2 items (Box 6)
      - Writings, 1852-1859; undated; 29 items (Box 6)
- Dr. William Mather Papers
  - Biographical and genealogical material
    See also Fairfield, New York: Biography and genealogy material (Box 1) and Alonzo C. Mather Papers: Biographical and genealogical material (Box 8)
    - Written by Dr. William Mather, 33 items (Box 7)
    - Obituaries, 1890; 2 items (Box 7)
  - Correspondence
    - Family
      - Incoming, 1836-1882; undated; 10 items (Box 7)
      - General, 1830-1851; 5 items (Box 7)
      - Children (collectively), 5 items (Box 7)
      - Mather, Mary (wife), 1849-1867; 8 items (Box 7)
    - General
      - A-W, 1839-1884; 30 items (Box 7)
      - Herkimer County National Bank, 1875-1882; 6 items (Box 7)
      - Mather, Horace, 1880-1882; 5 items (Box 7)
      - Silver, N—, 1869-1880; 9 items (Box 7)
    - Professional
      - A-W, 1829-1885; undated; 25 items
      - Outgoing, 4 items (Box 7)
  - Financial records, 10 items (Box 7)
  - Lectures
    - Correspondence, 1833-1859; undated; 10 items (Box 7)
    - Financial records
      - "Memorandums, Accounts, ...", 1851-1857; bound notebook; 1 item (Box 7)
      - Subscriptions, 1837-1847; 9 items (Box 7)
    - "Notes taken at medical lectures, Fairfield Medical College", 1827-1838; 12 items in 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Teaching material, 20 items (Box 8)
  - Photograph of Dr. William Mather, 1 item (Box 8)
  - Writings, includes resignation letter to the trustees of the college and "What I remember of James Fennimore (sic) Cooper" (original and copies); 18 items (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 5 items (Box 8)
- Alonzo C. Mather Papers
  - Biographical and genealogical material
    See also Fairfield, New York: Biography and genealogy material (Box 1) and Dr. William Mather Papers: Biographical and genealogical material (Box 7)
    - By Alonzo C. Mather, includes copy of Alonzo C. Mather's brief history of the Mather family and autobiography submitted to Courier-Journal circa 1884; 6 items (Box 8)
    - By others, includes copies of obituaries, notes about his life, and correspondence regarding the collection; 10 items (Box 8)
  - Correspondence
    See also Inventions and Professional Interests for additional correspondence related to specific projects.
    - Family correspondence
      - Mather, Mary Ann (mother), 1863-1874; undated; 6 items (Box 8)
      - Mather, Dr. William (father), 1865-1885; undated; 63 items in 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Parents, 1866-1872; 5 items (Box 8)
      - Watkins, Albert Barnes (brother-in-law), 1866; 4 items (Box 9)
      - Watkins, Martha Ann (sister), 1862-1870; undated; 17 items (Box 9)
      - Miscellaneous, 1890-1923; 11 items (Box 9)
    - General correspondence/subject files
      - A-W, 53 items (Box 9)
      - Auto, 1899-1901; 10 items (Box 9)
      - Blackmar, Esbon, 1902; resident of the Alliance; 12 items (Box 9)
      - Buffalo Concrete, Stone and Brick Company, 1904; 15 items (Box 9)
      - Doyle, General P. C. (Peter C.), 1893-1900; 8 items (Box 9)
      - Electricity and canal boats, 1893; 14 items (Box 9)
      - Fulton, Robert, 1893; 5 items (Box 9)
      - Inventive Age, 1893-1894; 4 items (Box 9)
      - Lazarus, Rosenfeld and Lehmann, 1901; 7 items (Box 9)
      - Mather, Horace E., 1895; 1897; 15 items (Box 9)
      - Price, J. Edward, 1901; regarding a coat of arms for the Alliance; 13 items (Box 9)
      - Rowland, Edward B., 1916-1918; 10 items (Box 9)
      - Scott, A. J., 1901-1902; 7 items (Box 9)
      - Thompson, Ellen B., 1901-1905; undated; regarding commission to copy works of art for Mather's art collection; 73 items in 4 folders (Box 9)
      - The Trumbull Manufacturing Company, 1900-1901; 1903; regarding plans for an automobile; 91 items in 3 folders (Box 10)
      - United States flag proposal, 1896; regarding Mather's design for the new 45-star flag; 78 items in 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Weapon collection, 1900-1901; 18 items (Box 10)
      - Wire nail machinery, 1902; 12 items (Box 10)
      - Yacht, 1898-1902; 46 items (Box 10)
  - Financial material
    - Checkbook, 1901; 1 items (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, 23 items (Box 11)
    - Invoices
      - General, 1900-1906; 19 items (Box 11)
      - Bowles, Frank, 9 items (Box 11)
      - Walbridge and Company, 1902-1903; 17 items (Box 11)
    - Personal Finances, 1922; 6 items (Box 11)
    - Southern Mutual Investment Company, 8 items (Box 11)
  - Inventions
    - Humane stock car
      - Correspondence/subject files
        - [General], 1881-1892; 30 items (Box 11)
        - Automatic couplers, 1891-1892; 8 items (Box 11)
        - Gasoline engine, 1892-1906; 9 items (Box 11)
        - Ripley, G. N., 1891; 17 items (Box 11)
      - Financial material
        - "Bills paid on a/c Mather's Humane Stock Trans. Co.", 1881; 28 items (Box 11)
        - Invoices, 1888-1889; 6 items (Box 11)
        - Statements, 1920; 17 items (Box 11)